who are you in and what's your divine
double mmm ooh oh that's one heck of an
opener Andrew yeah that's one heck of an
opener well well I don't know what to
say about that except that it's the
right question and I think that it's the
question that is it's the question that
is vectoring me through this series of
dialogic exercises and it's the question
that's vectoring me through my work with
John and my all of the work that I'm
that I'm absorbed in that has to do with
with with where we are in this
particular epoch within time and outside
of time and the meaning crisis all of
that work for me is in a way can be
formulated within the question what is
my divine double because I think that
that's the unfortunately it's kind of an
elliptical question for me right now
it's it's it's paving it's paving the
path of my pursuit but it's it's paving
it precisely because it's unanswered I
think that it has to do with the
espousal of vocation in the classic and
religious sense of the term and I think
that it has to do with understanding
with with knowing myself in a in a mode
of ongoing disclosure that that that
beckons me further into the world such
that being beckoned further into the
world is also being beckoned closer to
myself I don't know if that makes any
sense but I think there's a there's a
way in which the disclosure of the
project these projects that were you
know and I and I say we because I think
there's a way in which you're also
you're also absorbed in these projects
right I mean project in a very I mean it
very equivocal ii and the
that there are these there's a network
of interrelated projects that are
happening right now and you and I
perhaps serve are on different axes of
the project but they're part of the same
project fundamentally right and it's the
right the revolute the resolution of the
modern spiritual problem and the way
that that problem then disseminates
itself into all of the satellite
problems that we mistake for the problem
right yeah and and and the way that
translates into our our our politicking
and that kind of thing so I think that
for me as i as i immerse further into
the work myself becomes more and more
disclosed to me which is to say my my my
necessary role was the greeks damian
maybe of something like diamond yeah
exactly yeah yeah it's a diamond yeah
yeah that's right that's right very much
so yeah very much so right that that the
hermetic diamond that's that's the how
we usually think of arrows right the
thing that flips between domains mortal
and divine that bridges ourselves of
finitude into ourselves of infinitude
because I think what's meant by the
divine double in some sense and then you
put a bit of a character Guardian spin
on it but it's really the infinite
aspect the infinite aspect that that
composes the synthesis of self and I
think in some ways much of what we're
responding to right now and I say we
because I'm implicated is a loss of you
know it's it's a it's a it's a it's it's
no longer being able to find the divine
spark of the eternal within ourselves
right that connects us to the Li an
exhaustible and and so I guess the the
the hunt for my divine double is a a
it's it's a way of nosing out the
Eternity within within nosing out the
Eternity within the presence of the work
and the reflection of that eternity is
something like you know something like
the devil that you're talking yeah it's
interesting cuz I was me not answering
your question wrong no when he was with
you yeah yeah well there's there's an
aspect of humility to your answer which
but when he was saying that that you had
this sort of glimmer of feeling that you
have you know a gift for philosophy and
I was thinking that my feeling about you
was that you're kind of a poet
or at least I get a really poetic sense
in you in your writing which I thought
was very interesting
so it's interesting you're not slide
yourself my friend yeah well I'm not a
philosopher for sure you know I do my
best to try to understand philosophy but
in the past might I've pursued
songwriting and written above a poetry
and then I've moved on to sort of being
this kind of blogger
of some kind so so I feel like I I come
from from that that interest in actually
poetics rather than rather than let's
say straight up you know political stuff
or anything like that you know and and I
was thinking about what you were saying
about this sort of stale political air
that we get in and then trying to find a
sort of language but that liberates us
from that in some sense hmm am I am I
making am i are you following what I'm
saying yeah yeah perfectly yeah yeah
yeah absolutely absolutely yeah I think
that there's a great for me there's been
a great relief in finding the right
category of problem to grapple with
because the problem formulation like
like god it's everything which is why
your question so act right because it's
the right question and I think that
I mean so much of public discourse is
simply premise done on ill framed
questions and and entering into an arena
that has been that's been entering into
in it like you know an arena that has
been cordoned by by an ill-fated
question means that any discourteous
course that happens is also going to be
ill-fated right it's sort of like you're
damming yourself even by entering into
the discourse right because then because
I think of that old like that hold the
old Heraclitus maximum of character
being destiny but then they you know
character is destiny we see that about
about individuals but characterization I
think to take that in to extend it a
little bit characterization becomes
becomes destination so the way that we
characterize conversation the way we
embody the character of conversation
becomes its its its intellectual destiny
in addition to its dispositional destiny
right because the two things are
fundamentally linked which is why I'm
which is why that's why that's why Plato
is such a sin oh sure in my thinking
because Plato contains the the the
implicit the implicit understanding that
that that intellection is fleshed and we
have to understand it as fleshed and we
and we and we're always we're always
tempted to flesh it anyway that's why we
always resort to as a matter of course
we are arguments inevitably devolve into
ad hominem precisely because we have
this somehow we have this inkling that
that in your election is a process that
has to be somehow personified and that's
where the personification of
conversation I don't think as a I don't
think the personifying the process of
intellection is is I don't think that's
necessarily ill-fated but it also means
that the way we the way we assume
character in discourse is important and
it has everything to do with you know
how we T conversations up for one
another right well yeah we'll inevitably
determine house
that's what they are well I think that
was was kind of beautiful about your
conversation with ghee and Jordan and
John there's a kind of joy in the whole
process that's that is actually it's
almost tangible you can kind of feel it
that you guys are dancing with each
other
rather than sort of trying to crush each
other in the way that we do with our
with our personas and egos and and all
that right yeah yeah well I mean that's
just been a pleasure I kind of just feel
like I'm along for the ride in those
conversations because I mean just as
we're talking about in the conversation
itself there's a sense in which identity
absorbs into the process of the dialogue
and so you become things you become
persons that are then seemed to be
extrinsic to yourself in the throws of
the confrontations a confrontation sort
of implies implies discord I don't mean
to imply that by confrontation but
there's something about the the
accommodative confrontation in those
kinds of dialogues that presents you
with reflections of yourself that you
had yeah that's why that comes back to
your divine double question right it's a
process of having yourself revealed and
deepening and widening reflections the
deeper conversation goes you your your
your reflective image grows in
proportion to the depth of the
discussion which is why significant
discussions are so edifying it's not
just because they avail propositions
that we hadn't stumbled upon before it's
because ourselves are unfurled in the in
the process of those discussions that's
why they come out of them sometimes just
so utterly changed because it's like I'm
different now you know and that's why I
think of it enough sort of the Platonic
sense of recollection right it's like
the you are in potentia all things that
can be revealed in the throes of those
conversations so in a way it's like it's
a it's a kind of psychic homecoming
which I guess maybe sort of bridges it
into more of a Union thinking yeah I
notice the you often use the metaphors
of bird
thing and and I was thinking about that
and I was and and and being in a kind of
womb and this sort of creative process
of becoming something and and I was
thinking about four guys you know
getting together talking and and yet the
metaphor is always about is always about
birth so I know that's very interesting
and I don't mean to bring gender into
the subject we're so anima possessed but
but but but but but that seems to be
like something that gets guys very
excited or something that make any sense
because perhaps because they're not
they're not actually giving birth yeah
biological birth but but they want to be
involved in this process of giving birth
to ideas or that's right well that's
that's the the only way in which police
Asst is available to us is is you know
and that's why there's such a there's
such a deep powerful
that's why literal literal physical
poesis and and artistic polices are so
affined to one another if there's such
powerful assonance between those things
is because we have a sense in which they
are they are there is a continuity of
nature between physical birth and the
kind of police that we associate with
you know with with craftsmanship or or
whatnot and that kind of the way that
they're analogically bound to one
another I think again is something that
we find all the way back in Plato
there's a there's a very very powerful
there's a there's a there's it's almost
as though there's a symbolic embodiment
of one in the other and I think there's
something about that symbolic embodiment
there's some it's the the erotic
symbolic embodiment of the of the of the
notional and the somatic that's like
it's in a way it's indispensable and
it's and that's often much of what's
been lost to us right because of our
many modern many modern dualisms and so
on and and all and all kinds of things
have contributed
I don't want to oversimplify the problem
or or foisted on any one perpetrator
because that's often unfair to and
people do that a lot but I think that we
find ourselves so disembodied like
you're young you and I were talking
about that in our letter correspondence
right so yeah and there's this longing
for intimacy is another word that I I
see comes up a lot in your discussions
is this intimacy and and and and I think
the well the relief that I felt in
discussing this this letter what are you
doing this letter process with you
wasn't was to be able to communicate in
that way with the person I was find that
a lot of communication you know has
agendas to it and and that sort of thing
and and it's it's very refreshing to try
to enter a space of just pure creativity
and whatever you happen to be doing and
you know I was being set up with this
other person and right away it became a
tagging istic because apparently were
supposed to be on have different points
of view about something and it just
became painful and I didn't want to do
it but but there was something about
about your writing that just it was like
and you always use this metaphor in your
writing - you always talk about the
breath I felt like I could breathe
within your your world of writing so so
that was very nice and also felt thank
you for so I was felt that there I felt
that way too I was for you thank you and
I felt that I could I could I could take
something of yours and expand on it and
and that there was some kind of real
something really happening which it
doesn't always really happen in in your
sort of daily life and that's right
that's right
especially virtually I mean it almost
never happened on online this course
it's the kind of thing that often only
happens when people are mutually
disarmed by their physical proximity
right there's some there's something
humbling about being in physical
proximity to somebody because you have
to acknowledge that there is more in the
offing of the situation then there is
the semantic content of your discourse
and I think that's what physical
proximity does to people that disarms
their more invective impulses sometimes
so I'm not if not all the time but when
when when people get together to
discourse I think because there's so
much in the dynamic of the physical
confrontation that has nothing to do
with the propositional content mm-hmm
that that marginalia that that that that
intuitive marginalia the edge of the
conversation gets to spill in to the
dynamic a little bit more mm-hmm
which is something also true if now the
video conferencing that we're able to do
which is also nice right because you
have all of the things that aren't the
propositional content some of some of
that at least can then pour in some of
it all of that of course is oh yeah and
all of that context of course is is
removed from the virtual interaction and
I think that's that's often why it
becomes it becomes opaque because it
there's no there's nothing - there's
nothing - there's no humiliating again I
mean it in a sense of like humility
there's no yeah there's nothing - to
properly to properly espouse humility
within it and and that's why right and
the video gives you a bit of that not
the whole picture but a bit but it does
also yeah it disarms you in a way and
which which you you kind of feel like
you're like a false god on the internet
and on some level you're like a demigod
right you feel like you can do all that
you have all this power yeah yeah but
you don't you but but but then it's it's
a sterile kind of power until it's
grounded in intimacy and no maybe that's
why you can this birthing let metaphor
keeps coming up because we're so longing
to be grounded in intimacy because we're
so pulled out of it all the time I think
so i think that i think sterile is
exactly the right word for the for the
virtual discourse most of it most
because because the people are to
themselves on like on I mean social
media is an easy whipping boy but you
know it's easy it's an easy whipping
for a reason I suppose the way people
are on something like Facebook or
comparable social media outlets is that
you know they've they've conceived of
themselves as something something fixed
inside time that has that is bounded
that is bounded and has a particular
essence of identity that is that is
relatively unmoved for so now that you
were talking about it a persona yeah
yeah you're creating a persona all the
time you're sort of all the time and
that's why there's no there's and and
that's why at the end there's a brittle
there's a there's a brittleness to that
persona because we all know that they're
not real um
but yet people continue to invest in
them and I think riddle is it's not
strong enough a word I think there's a
there's a violence even and you know how
people communicate these days like
anyway yes no you're right yeah you're
right you're right yeah so whatever the
opposite of fertile intimate interaction
is that's the kind that happens that's
the kind of how that happens on these
platforms because all we're concerned
about is how we appear like that's the
problem it's like all we're concerned
about is how is semblance you know how
we seem and and that's not like it's
just not a sustainable way to live it's
just not it I mean it has very specific
instrumental utility at times word
exercising you know certain you know you
have to play that it has I get the most
basic and the most basic functional
sense it has some utility but as a way
of investing of yourself I think it's I
think it's fundamentally misguided and
I'm actually not convinced people make
many arguments some more compelling than
others for why the existence of these
virtual tools I mean specifically the
social media kind why they're virtues
whether whether virtues redeem their
their moral failings and I'm not
convinced at all that any of their
virtues are sufficiently redemptive to
justify their existence frankly it's a
bit of a hard it's a bit of a it's a bit
of a hard line to take but I really well
I think I think it's 99% noise and if it
ever gets to a level where there's a
little bit more signal than noise or a
little bit more good way of putting it a
little bit more content and and and then
bullshit where you know and then just a
little bit more wood wood wood but at
least at least allow for something like
I think what you guys are doing actually
in your and your four-way conversations
that that strikes me as something new in
the positive sense because it's like
you're creating a a four person mind or
something you're creating a team a team
mind and it's like like John was saying
in that conversation that he probably
couldn't have thought of that without
the other three people being there so if
that that kind of that mech that's
that's that's sort of mind-blowing to me
and I think that's like that has to be
that that's the sort of counter reaction
to to to Facebook which is atrocious and
in all the ways you're saying mmm that's
right that's right and that and that
you're right and that is what I think
that the video the video platform you
know things like YouTube or practice
primarily YouTube I'm not fluent enough
in the landscape to be able to yeah
offer a suite of comparisons but yeah
that I think I I do hold that obviously
I would have to otherwise this exercise
would be hypocritical of me I do hold
that in to be a different category for
for its for its potential to actually
foster proper relating your yeah I think
the way the signal signal noise
observation that you just made is also
quite that's a good insight I think
that's exactly right to so I also like I
want to know just a little bit of
like like you like your you're a young
guy you seem to be sort of wise beyond
your years and years and years you might
be on my ears maybe you're older than
you look or something but but I'm just
I'm just ready when I was 30 I was
pretty much of a schmuck I think again
it goes comes back to the my first
question is how you developed this
interesting truth or it's their scene
you seem to have a spiritual side to you
as well and but what happened to you or
is there anything you can share here
that wouldn't be you know indiscreet or
that wouldn't be tuned to screen um well
I I have thank you first of all Andrew
that you're very very kind and and I can
be quite a schmuck yeah I've seen me
when I was 30 I guess we all have our
moments don't we um but you that was
very kind of you thank you um I think I
I have a I was I have an original and
very distinct advantage in my life in
the form of a very well-adjusted and
deeply deeply loving family I think that
doll starts there for me there can be no
doubt of that in my mind that most
molten you know the the then because
then for me the knowing of the good
begins there in my life the knowing of
the good begins yeah yeah but I was I
mean I was born and raised here in
Cannon se on Toronto so so that it's a
it's a it it it backgrounds my my
familial identity but it's not the
center of it my parents were also both
born they were there both from Montreal
so they're also Canadian you know born
and raised so so it's a fairly I would
say it's a fairly Canadian ice-t--
family whatever that means
you know I'm Canadian - right I I will
instead we haven't gotten there yet but
I'm going to ask you all about yourself
and asking
one of my first questions okay because I
gathered I mean I know you live in Paris
but but just based on our correspondence
I gather that you have connections a lot
of connections here so I assume you're
from here yep I am yeah okay and I first
Ragno specifically or else where my
parents live it live in Ottawa I have a
lot of family in Toronto and I studied
at McGill so the development for many
years okay but I've been here since 2003
so so um maybe I've lost some of my
Canadian miss but interesting okay I see
I want to ask you all about okay we're
gonna get back to that okay let's let's
keep really want to know what that has
meant for you that transition okay okay
we'll get there we'll get there yeah um
okay what was this yeah so I think that
you know I I was I was I have so I have
a very sort of the matrix of my family
life was very encouraging and the proper
sense of the term and and also just very
just very affectionate and very and and
open hoping in the sense that you know
there weren't a lot of aside from just
being generally you know responsible and
and competent and being just being
adjusting to the degree that he become a
a well-put-together person there weren't
a lot of there weren't a lot of
prescribed expectations as to what I
needed to do or be and that kind of
thing and also that we were back rounded
religiously insofar as the family was
Catholic but but it was Catholic in a
very equivocal sense of the term I think
or perhaps a very typical sense of the
term I think for many Canadian Catholics
you know you have the Christmas and
Easter Catholics and we were kind of
that but my my parents are both
religiously open by disposition which
means that they had an appreciation for
the fact that it was and is important
but also that the way that it is going
to be articulated in our lives doesn't
doesn't necessarily have to be
overweening or or or or tyrannical or
dogmatic so I think I was lucky too
have I was lucky too right off the bat I
was raised into a family that had a
relatively well-adjusted idea of what of
the fact that that a religious a
religious life and education and
literacy was important but that that
that it had to be it also had to be had
to be mitigated by by by a realization
that there you know there's a lot that's
there's a lot that's there's a lot
that's not working right now about it so
I think I you know I kind of got that
that was like that I kind of came with
that and and I think that was that
disposed me from the beginning to be to
be I think what it did actually when I
think about it when I think of my sort
of my younger self I think and not that
I know I could certainly become I don't
know like like the best yeah like it
like any other young man I could be very
I could be very sort of you know
recalcitrant about about these things
but I think that ultimately I think that
my foot my family life did is it
indoctrinated me and indoctrination me
inoculated me wow what a Freudian slip
it inoculated me against the dangers of
both of both fundamentalism and a
Fletcher gotcha I think that's what it
did like the great the great gifts that
my parents for instance gave me I think
among many of the great gifts implicit
me they didn't close it talking about
dogmatic religion or no or to all the
poetry from you with you know the sort
of positivist yeah they didn't they were
not hostile toward it but they were also
not they were also know
not yeah they were not mired in problems
of literalism and and so I think that
that kind of got now beyond that I think
that they largely left me alone to to
figure this out for myself but I think
that that was a heck of a good start
because and that I had an appreciation
for all that I didn't know and and and
there wasn't there wasn't but I wasn't
prescribed - I wasn't prescribed to dawn
any specific garb or affiliate with his
was avid tribe and that kind of thing
and now what that did is I think that
gave me a bit of a feeling of Mattacks
ooh a feeling of being in between that's
that's still I still have and I struggle
with it it isn't it isn't day I mean I
think it has advantage to me in a lot of
ways but it has also it has also
challenged me in a lot of ways because
even now I'm always in between I'm
always always in between categories of
thinking and that's very very difficult
that's right I mean you wanted like
that's my story basically every part of
every leg every leg of the journey is
simply another version of being in
between categories of thinking and in
between in between disciplines in
between commitments in between camps and
I just perpetually perpetual in between
this of course now with a little bit of
eff a little bit a little bit more
philosophically and literate I
understand that there's some there's a
symbolic significance to being in
between and I think this is why I always
come back to the the nature of Eros that
hermetic nature of Eros right for the
diamond by the socratic diamond as a
perpetual in betweenness and I
identified very very very closely with
that my friend Alexander talks about a
shamanic caste he does something called
no-no madala G where he looks at early
tribes and he said he says there's about
4% of the population there kind of in
between they go in between tribes
you know they're they could be diplomats
or they could be you know they could be
priests well more like shamans or now
they would go in between oh they would
always be the end right well because
they wouldn't yeah it wouldn't have a
fixed you know well that their role
would be would be that would be would
would not be a fixed role within the
tribe but somebody who could go outside
the tribe and talk to other tribes and
mm-hmm that makes any sense it does it
makes a lot of sense I can t very much
relate to that as well and you yeah do
you feel that of yourself as well yeah
definitely
yeah yeah because well first of all I'm
in between by virtue of living in a
foreign country so I'm in between Canada
and horse and I'm in between in the
sense that you know I've been a
practicing Buddhist since I was in my
20s so and I'm in a Christian you know
and I have a Christian you know
worldview so so I'm in-between sort of
you know sort of that and when I when I
hear you talk about that and want to
hear I hear John talk about that the
religion of without the religion or
something like that it's like it's like
I think being an in-between person is
somebody who sort of has a lot of
sympathy for a lot of different kind of
people and different views of worldviews
and and sort of relates to the world
through through a kind of kind of I
guess you know just sort of sort of
sympathy rather than then judgment or if
that makes any sense I think it does I
think it I think flitting in between
different different camps does give you
a a certain
oh yeah I think it requires a little I
think it requires a certain amount of
pliability and and and flexibility and
agree and agreeable agreeableness I have
over hats I'm very low on that test
actually I'm are you well then
interesting okay that's a medicine I I'm
lower I'm lower probably lower than you
I'm not I'm not I'm not an in-between
diplomat type of person I'm in between
and in the sense of of being probably in
a more ID tagging istic way than you are
like I refuse to be this or that right
ah interesting interesting interesting
interesting yes yes yes okay so that we
political about you know about yes or
something like that or a few yes
I refuse to be fully religious but I
refuse not to be religious as well you
know it's like it's like yes and I'm
right with right there with you in that
respect as well I
yeah you rigid again it's a question of
rejecting rejecting the premise of a
conversation it's like you're wrong and
you're wrong because the question is
wrong so sorry I'm outside the arena on
this one yeah I die yeah I have a bit of
that I have a bit of that obdurate
temperament to when it comes to just
refusing participation in fact it's
funny entering into this world this this
world of this world of discourse that
you and I are instantiating in this
conversation I had a lot of apprehension
about doing it because yeah - right and
because it's it's well because it had
all the dangers of all the dangers that
I was always so weary of I was just
talking about this with a friend of mine
the other day I feel like I'm always
alternating between the dangerous of the
imposter syndrome dangers and then the
inflation dangers and so terrified of
both of them that that I often my
resolution often defaults into and into
some kind of some form of abstinence
which is not a you know it is an
instinct and not a properly
contemplative solution which is why I
think the foray into these discourses
for me has been helpful yeah I need any
disposition anyway you do it anyway
right
even though somehow I remember just the
first kind of video conversation I have
with people feeling this incredible like
resistance to the whole thing like with
the earphones and in the screens and and
everything it's just like what the hell
is going on here and what yeah what am i
doing why am I doing this and what is
this it's like alien territory or
something and that's right I'm getting
more comfortable with it as time goes by
but I'm not comfortable with it I
wouldn't say I was comfortable with it I
would say I said I say over time it
becomes a medium that that I can swim in
a little bit but right in the beginning
of yeah it feels it feels like a
struggle right
well your your sort of your your your
courage and toleration of it I think
exceeds mine because you I think you've
actually entered into discussions with
people that are that are like overtly
opponent conversations right yeah have
you done yeah yeah I'm not I'm not yeah
I I tend to I tend to have a fighting
spirit with people yeah that's true
yeah right right so maybe that's part of
the temperamental difference so we were
just yeah sort of continent on - yeah
yeah because I think that that a
conversation at least a public
conversation that's inflected with
genuine debate yeah I mean it's one
thing if it's if it's in the socratic if
it's in the if it's in the Socratic
spirit of challenge for the purpose of
resituated yeah that's one thing that's
great that's just part of that's part of
that's part of philosophy but if it's if
well if John John John always calls it
Philo an Ikea if it's if it's about the
if it's a if it's a game that is if it's
a game that's going to figure a victor
then I'm I'm just disinterested who
cares about winning yeah yeah yeah well
both in both lose as far as I'm
concerned like do you know not and now
it's funny I I and I don't know how I
feel I don't know how I feel about I
mean so much of the academic culture is
is frames its discursive arenas in the
form of debates that have a sense of
winners or losers and I don't know I
don't know if that whole enterprise is
just watched and should just be really
quit right or or if there is some
utility to it it has its place and its
place has just become inflated and
encompassing I'm not sure how I feel
about that yet but I think I might have
an insight into that well anyway I often
bring in a you know masculinity I've
talked a lot about masculinity often
because it's such a taboo topic and and
and nobody likes to talk about it and I
think that I think there's something
about about guys men who they need to
fight on some level sometimes in some
kind of a way and if they're doing that
in an academic setting maybe they're
maybe they're not doing it in the
setting of war like maybe there is sort
of a healthy form of fight of a fight
you know I know people who loved you
know love that kind of thing I love to
be a nag and get into it just get into a
good scrap with somebody there's a place
for it you're right it's important well
because it's because implicitly it's
it's an inextricable part of our nature
and it has to be exercised and
integrated and so then the question
becomes how do we integrate it let me
ask part of what Peterson's project is
right the especial of existential
responsibility is about integrating
integrating and situating aggression
within the psyche in such a way that it
becomes subordinate to the holistic hood
of the self and I think that that I
think that's a--that's a deeply deeply
meaningful project deeply meaningful
project I think my sense is though that
it's a project that cannot be conflated
with the project of genuine
philosophical inquiry like they have to
somehow be disliked they have to be
dispossessed of one another's influence
and I don't know how that happens
exactly like it's sort of like you know
when you when you're when you're when
you're when you're having a tiff with
somebody sometimes it's good to sit down
and just just throw down fight it out
yeah maybe not physically or maybe
physically but sit down have your
argument but I think there has to be the
game you're playing is not a game of
propositions it's a game of it's a it's
a baser game of resolving latent
aggression that then threatens to engulf
your propositional fingering and and and
I think once you resolve that and maybe
resolving it just means indulging it for
a period of time legs within safe
parameters but indulging it do that's
what that's what wrestling it would be
right it'd be two people's right respect
each other maybe even love each other a
lot wrestling it out like physically I
mean that's right that seems to be a
beautiful thing if the right spirit is
is behind it that's right
that's right exactly and that's why
combat of sports like things like MMA or
you know boxing or like there's a reason
that they're so popular and it's because
like we found a relative I mean safe as
a relative term I suppose I might get
pretty intense but we found a relatively
safe arena in which to exercise the
aggressive impulse and and give it
geometry within a game that can that can
control it and that can that can
integrate it now I don't know if that's
a perfect integration but it's I think
it's an attempt to do that and I think
there's a place for that there's a place
for that but I kind of think of it but
more into personally and and more and
more conversationally I think it's sort
of like it's sort of like the difference
you know you're you're having a conflict
with somebody and there are genuine
there are genuine like there are genuine
perspectival problems that you need to
that you need to sort out with one
another you know you do need to engage
to a Socratic process of under
standing the situation so that you can
so that you can that you can bring sort
of elucidation to a problem but
sometimes before you can actually do
that like when two people meet each
other yeah there's a there's a there's a
film that said that just came out called
marriage story yeah I saw that yeah yeah
yeah and thinking about that as well and
there's you know there's that sort of
there's there's there's there's so much
there's so much I mean there's so much
ambivalence it's fraught with
ambivalence which is what makes it like
very very similar its but and I'm not
I'm I'm I'm not married so you you can
probably ear are you so you you can
speak for experientially on this topic
than I can but anyway I guess the point
is that there's all this sort of latent
aggression that that that exists sort of
beneath the surface but both parties
both both both spouses are trying so
hard to be as to touch me as my civilly
as possible
you know and then a guy just bangs his
head against the wall enters the wall
right right well then they had that
scene where they nurse Throwdown and
it's is ostensibly about resolving their
circumstances and coming to a shared
understanding but there's no hope of
doing that until they have their
opportunity to throw down and to tell
one another how much they hate one
another and how they've ruined each
other's lives and that they wish each
other were dead and then once they've
got that out of the way then from that I
think this is no it's no coincidence
from that from that point on it's a it's
a fulcrum for the story because after
that point in the story they actually
start to be able to cohere what around a
more sustainable and viable model for
their relationship going forward but
they need to they need it to have that
absolute Throwdown but the real
aggression we're able to do that the
real aggression is in to just the being
nice all the time now
the real aggression like the real
aggression is before the actual physical
aggression comes out yes yes self
containment and which which Lee saw this
self-hatred and then this sort of
pussyfooting around and and and and
everybody's trying to be Noble and you
know they're both trying to be be
something and yeah that's right it gets
very painful until until that moment
where you have this this physical
release or this like that suddenly
there's suddenly they can they can they
have some reality or some yeah that's
right yeah yeah you need that like
moment of just sheer that that's your
tempest of it because because they like
they have to realign the reason that
they're that kind of conversation just
devolves into into into gladiatorial
combat after a while is because they
have to abandon the pretense that their
conversation is about any of the
propositions that they're making to
unknown right and and the the
propositional content simply serves to
gesture to the the authentic source of
the conflict and and and but they need
they need to trade in exchange the
propositions in order to find their way
to the crux of the conflict and then
allow it to to to to emergent and and
come forth and be aired and addressed
properly so that after that point they
can actually start to have to converse
so they can have the proper Socratic
dialogue you know so they're nothing
do not just caught in these webs of you
know self-doubt and you know trying to
be good or bad or whatever that's right
that's right and that's I mean that's
that's when subtext is rendered rendered
well in any piece of art it has to do
with that right it has to do with what's
what really are we talking about when
we're talking to one another right now
are we are we are we talking about a
relation that is epistemic ly oriented
or are we talking about a relation that
is that is that is adversarially
oriented and if we're talking about the
latter
propositional content all its going to
do is it's going to dig us in the
direction of our of our adversarial
tension so hopefully if we're learning
our lessons from that then we simply let
the adversarial tension erupt yeah and
have it stay so that we can move on and
then maybe there's a yeah well we have
to get it maybe this could this this
touches on sort of the our original
conversation which was about monsters
right mmm no it touches on on you know
being able to live with let's say the
monster in yourself or being able to
allow it to come out and to see it and
because because if you bottle it up for
your whole life you you know it's gonna
do damage to you on some level mmm-hmm
that's right that's right that's exactly
right that's exactly it will it will it
will always mmm we're always possessed
right and then the question is how are
we possessed what's the nature of the
possession mmm yeah that's right that's
right that's right so let me let me
maybe take this opportunity if you don't
mind stretch it to kind of to turn to
turn the attention a little bit in your
day go for it oh all kinds of stuff
about you that I'm so curious to know
yeah and and I guess you you provided me
with a little bit of a segue earlier so
why don't I just pick up that thread I
so you were you're from from Canada
originally you spent some time in were
educated in Montreal and then you you
moved to Paris in the early 2000s what
was so first of all what would you mind
me asking what brought you to to Paris
in the first time well IIIi I ended up
it was sheer accident I was it was a you
know I met somebody I moved here and
ended up staying I guess that gets back
to the the the in betweenness that we
were talking about that you sort of
straddle identification with two
different senses of home or two
different places
how has that resolved in your sense of
personal identity both in your
activities and the things that you love
to do but just also sort of the
attitudes that you have
sort of quotidian basis mmm well I'm a
happily married guy and with two two
kids and I just bought a home so this is
all congratulations and this is about us
like adult I'm 48 so this is as adult as
I've been able to muster up in my 20s I
wanted to be a songwriter so I wrote
hundreds of songs and I lived in
Montreal and I have played in bands
I kind of was I was I was I would I
would say I was a poor student but I was
a big reader mmm so I read a lot and and
I was always reading and I was always
trying trying to translate the books I
read into into songs and that was I did
that I did I it all the way up until
like I still do that actually but I
still write I still write songs but but
somehow that is being translated
creatively these days into into writing
writing and podcasting and traveling
around and meeting people and talking to
people like you you know I I'm a teacher
at I teach it I'm a sort of supplied
teacher at different universities here
that's how I learned my enough to
survive and so I teach one class on
actually it's called monsters it's very
interesting I my class I taught I did a
class on zombies and then I discovered
your book and and I was like wow this
was this was what I was sort of this was
articulating all these places I was
going and trying and teaching it in my
class and oh that's cool you seem to
have this interesting sort of
Renaissance skillset that that year
you're and you were talking a little bit
about this earlier that you sort of you
you have all of these you have linkages
to a lot of different interests that all
seem to find their Nexus and you a
combination of artistic and and academic
and and musical and literary like you
seem to be at a crossroads of all of
these converging talents and and
interests which is which is which is
neat and and unsurprising because you
seem you seem so broadly versed and so
broadly literate and it doesn't surprise
me that your
it's be seem to be attacked at a
convergence of a lot of different a lot
of a lot of different just just a
Anahata and a sort of rested at a hub of
different different talents hmm yeah
well yeah again I never I never I always
I was always liked writing and I still
I'm still not in terms of finding what
the divine double is I'm always
struggling back and forth between
writing and music and and which which
archetype is is me and I don't know if I
figured it out yet
I don't know figure if I figured it out
exactly precisely what I was doing what
I what I am doing actually you know in
my 20s I was pretty sure I wanted to
write songs and I was pretty damn sure
about that and I kind of had no interest
in anything else and that was just I was
just like that and also while there's I
should say that I lived in various
Buddhist monasteries here and there and
travelled for I spent a year in a
monastery and I also was also glad to do
basic interests what works for spiritual
practice and and songwriting up until
now now in the past five years my
interest has moved from songwriting to
writing and the spiritual practice
interest continues so so those are the
two those are the two big things I guess
and you certainly have found like
there's something's it seems that with
your with your with your your site or
your channel and not sure what you call
it but your your your space on medium or
you go you write essays very regularly
you've sort of you seem to have taken on
the identity of an essayist yeah degree
and that's an interesting that's an
interesting coalescence of the different
the different identities that you've
seemed to be alternating between there's
you've rested somewhere very interesting
yeah si means to try but to answer a
question
mmm that's right doesn't it so sorry so
even even writing an essay is that why
am i doing is this kind of a question
that I'm trying to answer I know there's
something dialogic in your essaying
mm-hmm there's a conversation
conversation that you're casting out the
question of what one should be doing at
any given moment in time is a very
difficult question to answer
yeah it's a very very difficult question
to answer yeah that's that's and that's
an important question that's one a
question that one should be asking all
the time isn't it and that is your that
is your that in a way about a spiritual
practice right yes should I be doing
this very very moment that's right
that's right and I think that there's a
way in which to quite these questions
I'll share identity because the question
of what ought I to be doing and the
question of who who am i fundamentally
which is of course your question about
the divine double that that central
question kala gates all of these other
questions because if I know if I know
myself I also know what I must be doing
and if I know what I must be doing then
I also know myself because there's a
verbal nature to the knowing of oneself
right in the sense of being of verb and
so you know yours I think there's a the
knowing of oneself as an ism is an
activity certainly over and above being
some kind of some kind of proposition or
some kind of silhouette in tableau right
it's an its emotional knowledge that's
what makes it gnosis right it's a it's a
conformed activity when you get that
feeling that you see you have some your
steps have if only temporarily come into
stride with your double or come within
within range of the stride of your
double yeah then suddenly you find
yourself sort of cresting to yourself
properly and yeah Ralphy says every
angel is terrifying it's like you come
you you sort of see this chair you see
this now you have this taste of total
freedom on some level and then you come
back to yourself in your life
yeah that's right that's right
you that's right yes yes and that's why
I think that's why it's a job it's such
an that can be such an alienating
experience because you you come to
yourself in the throes of some some very
meaningful exercised and then when you
pass through it to the other side of it
you're changed because you know that
anything else that you might be doing at
least I feel this way you know when when
I find myself when I find myself caught
in the right you know dancing to the
right rhythm you know caught in the
right flow whatever whatever metaphor we
may choose here it's a neck stasis of an
experience but it also means that it it
ruins much of the rest of your life
right because yeah because you can't
because everything is so drab compared
to that right everything yeah yeah is
gray and you know not interesting and
yeah everything seems to be so inane and
and dumb and banal by by comparison and
and I struggle with that a lot I
struggle with being overwhelmed by by
over I mean meaningfully overwhelmed by
by um by activities that seem to have
some ultimate import activities that are
eternal gestures and as it were right
that partake of between the gestures
that are better better better about the
always as best Paul Fenech really say I
love the way he makes that distinction
but but then when you have to when you
have to then come back into the
day-to-day yeah and that's the hard work
actually I think in a way it's just
embodying that it's like yeah it's
really hard it's really hard to embody
that
it is some people are very grounded and
they they need to climb upwards you know
other people are sort of in a sublime
realm when they have to climb downwards
into the body or something I don't know
if that makes any sense I'm just it does
it does uh-huh it does and I think it
has something to do with that it's
something to do with being neither here
nor there that we were talking about -
yeah there's something about - just
being um I think that that there's
something simultaneously freeing and
challenging about having a assuming the
identity of uh of an amateur when it
comes to these kinds of conversations
and I and I still think of myself that
way um so do you know the Italian root
of the word amateur right
it's like mature is something to do with
love being a lover of something right
right no I'd forgotten that
thank you for reminding me of that yes
yes something rather than a professional
right uh-huh yeah right right yes yes
that's right that's right that's right
that's right that's right so that yeah
that bespeaks the point beautifully but
the challenge in that is that when you
do something as an amateur I was trip
just happy just before we started
talking about a discussion with a friend
of mine about how how dysphoric and dis
regulating love can be and there is
something dysphoric and dis regulating
about espousing an amateurish love
towards something so ultimately
important it's very vulnerable isn't it
it's it's very it's very extreme
vulnerability I think it is extreme
vulnerability but
but I'm starting to realize like I'm
starting to realize that the extreme
vulnerability is actually the only way
it's the it's the only thing that's
going to properly conduce the
transformative experience required to
then progress further I think that's
right characterized wait right you need
like you need it I'm starting by should
so you know I shouldn't be so quick to
generalize my my my my reflexive
insights but I think I need it and I
think I'm starting to realize how
essential it is I didn't know I think
you can stick with your original and
insight and say that it's it's actually
it's it's it's the only way yeah yeah
yeah took it in a way I guess if I was
to put a more sort of existential
formulation on I would say the
realization that you are not yourself
the realization not to be oneself comes
with the comes with an existential
prescription that you must take the
steps to be oneself you know and like
realizing the realizing the in identic
allottee I think is very helpful like
when you wake up one day and think no
I'm not I'm not being myself
right now that naturally like
automatically it invokes that it's it's
it's correlating the longings
prescription yeah the longing the
longing right yeah the realization that
somebody wants to spirit the despaired
to despair not to be oneself yeah some
wise person once told me I said you know
where do I start I was like where do you
start and you always start with longing
right that's what that's where you start
hmm yeah that's right that's right
exactly exactly you start with your we
start with insufficiency and longing or
your that's right that's right that's
right and then I think what you try and
do and this is what that I mean this is
this is precisely the Socratic project
is you take that inkling of this
insufficiency and then you reproduce the
insufficiency at every level of your
awareness so that you actually compel
yourself
comprehensively to turn in the direction
of what will be more saving right it's
like that's what that's that the
function of the Platonic myths that's
what the function of autonomous people
like Jonathan there's notice that's that
the function of Plato's myths was to
imbue the the more somatic appetitive
parts of the psyche with the same
dissatisfaction as the intellectual
faculties so that you you you
essentially you embody the descent the
intellect sort of the intellectual
dissatisfaction becomes embodied
somatically and become and so that you
can coordinate yourself more
comprehensively to refocus on the
project of of orienting yourself to what
will be more satisfying right so if
there's something about like filling
yourself up with dissatisfaction is a
project that seems awfully strange out
of context but I think in many ways I
think it's dissatisfaction is something
that you have to cultivate before you
can cultivate the project of satisfying
yourself you have to allow yourself to
embody your dissatisfaction so
thoroughly that you whet your appetite
for for for for a more substantial
transformation